Guide to the Ralph Waldo Emerson Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ralph Waldo Emerson collection
1793-1937
YCAL MSS 212
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.54
(2 boxes) + 1 art + 1 broadside folder
The Emerson collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, and prints documenting the life and work of Ralph Waldo Emerson.
Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882
Pirsson, Eliza Brush
Sutton, Henry Septimus
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Ralph Waldo Emerson (1803-1882)
American author.
Scope and Contents
The Ralph Waldo Emerson Collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, and artwork documenting the life and work of Ralph Waldo Emerson.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, 1837-1877. II. Kenneth W. Cameron Gifts, 1793-1871. III. Julia Millhiser Gimbel Gift, 1872. IV. Eliza Brush Pirsson Gift, 1848-1932. V. Material from Other Sources, 1832-1937.
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Concord (Mass.); Daguerreotypes (photographs) -- United States -- 19th century; Engravings (prints) -- United States -- 19th century; Lithographs -- United States -- 19th century; Photographic prints -- United States -- 19th century; Photogravures (prints) -- United States -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century; Alger, William Rounseville, 1822-1905; Allingham, William, 1824-1889; Botta, Anne C. Lynch (Anne Charlotte Lynch), 1815-1891; Carlyle, Thomas, 1795-1881; Cowdin, Elliot C. (Elliot Christopher), 1819-1880; Cross, Wilbur L. (Wilbur Lucius), 1862-1948; Emerson, Ellen Tucker; Emerson, P. H. (Peter Henry), 1856-1936; Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882; Emerson, William, 1769-1811; Fields, James Thomas, 1817-1881; Ganz, Charles; Linton, W. J. (William James), 1812-1897; Neuberg, Joseph, 1806-1867; Pirsson, Eliza Brush; Pirsson, Louis V. (Louis Valentine), 1860-1919; Ross, Alexander Milton, 1832-1897; Scudder, Townsend, 1900-; Towne, E. C. (Edward Cornelius), 1834-1911; Royal Photographic Society of Great Britain
- Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, 1837-1877; Series I; 12
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence consists of letters from Emerson to others, including author and clergyman William Rounseville Alger, Anne C. Botta, publisher James Thomas Fields, and William James Linton. There are three autograph manuscript leaves of the manuscript Parnassus.
  Custodial History
  Gift of Owen Franklin Aldis, 1911.
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Writings.
  - Correspondence
    - Alger, [William Rounseville?], 1856 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Blake, H. G. O. (Harrison Gray Otis), 1848 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Botta, Anne C. Lynch (Anne Charlotte Lynch ), 1871, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Child, Lydia Maria [Francis], 1855 Nov 11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dwight, J. S., 1837, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Fields, James Thomas, 1865 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Harvey, A. W., 1850 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Mrs. Landei, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Linton, W. J. (William James), 1877 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Pedder, Bessie, 1860 Nov 29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Writings
    - "Parnassus," three leaves, autograph manuscript, circa 1875 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Kenneth W. Cameron Gifts, 1793-1871; Series II; 7
  Correspondence contains several outgoing letters, including three letters to Irish poet William Allingham, and one third party letter from Emerson's father William to his sister Rebecca. Writings contains autograph manuscript notes for a lecture on Emerson by Henry Septimus Sutton.
  Gifts of Kenneth W. Cameron, 1958-1959.
  Series II is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Writings.
  - Correspondence
    - Letters from Ralph Waldo Emerson
      - To Allingham, William, 1848-1852 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - To [Hall, Francis?], 1853 Oct 7 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - To Matthews, William, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - To Webb, Richard Davis, 1871 Jan 26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - To Welford, Marianne, 1849 Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Third-party correspondence
      - William Emerson to Rebecca Emerson, 1793 Oct 3 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Writings, 1848
    - Sutton, Henry Septimus
      - Lecture notes, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
        General
        Includes photograph of Emerson.
- Julia Millhiser Gimbel Gift, 1872; Series III; 6
  The Gimbel gift contains a single letter from Emerson to Edward Cornelius Towne and autograph manuscripts of five poems.
  Gift of Julia Millhiser Gimbel, 1974.
  Series III is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Writings.
  - Correspondence
    - Towne, E. C. (Edward Cornelius), 1872 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Writings
    - "The Amulet," poem, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Each and All, " poem, autograph manuscript, corrected and bound, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Includes reproduction of engraving by Timothy Cole
    - "The Poet," chorus, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - ''Sursum Corda," poem, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - "Terminus," poem, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Includes note in unidentified hand.
- Eliza Brush Pirsson Gift, 1848-1932; Series IV; 13
  The Pirsson gift includes third-party correspondence relating to Emerson and Thomas Carlyle, drafts of a manuscript by Pirsson, and a daguerreotype of Emerson. There are letters between Eliza Brush Pirsson, Louis Valentine Pirsson, and Wilbur L. Cross, and one letter from Carlyle to Joseph Neuberg.
  Series IV is organized into two subseries: Third-party Correspondence and Other Material.
  Gift of Eliza Brush Pirsson, 1947.
  - Third-party Correspondence
    - To Louis Valentine Pirsson
      - Cross, Wilbur L. (Wilbur Lucius), 1915 Jun 17 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Frankau, [F. J.?], 1913-1919 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Pirsson, Eliza Brush, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
        Includes copies of undated letter from Edward Waldo Emerson to Wilbur L. Cross in Pirsson's hand
    - To and from Eliza Brush Pirsson
      - Cross, Wilbur L. (Wilbur Lucius), 1915, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Frankau, [F. J.?], 1914-1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
    - To Joseph Neuberg
      - Carlyle, Jane W., 1848 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 32)
        Typescript copies, one with undated note from Townsend Scudder to an unidentified recipient.
      - Carlyle, Thomas, 1862 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Other Third-party Correspondence
      - Frankau, [F. J.?] to Townsend Scudder, 1932 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Other Material
    - "A New Portrait of Emerson" by Eliza Brush Pirsson
      - Research notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Drafts, holograph and typescript carbon, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Daguerreotype of Emerson, undated (Box 37 (Art))
- Material from Other Sources, 1832-1937; Series V; 27
  Correspondence includes letters from Emerson to Elliot C. Cowdin and Alexander Milton Ross. There are third-party letters from Emerson's daughter, Ellen Tucker Emerson, and from Peter Henry Emerson. Other letters to Charles Ganz from the British Journal of Photography and the Royal Photographic Society of Great Britain concern the death of British photographer Peter Henry Emerson, a distant relative. Artwork contains photographs of Emerson and his home in Concord, Massachusetts, and representations of Emerson in engravings, a lithograph, and a photogravure.
  Series V is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Artwork, and Other Material.
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources. Sources are indicated on individual folders.
  - Correspondence
    - Letters from Ralph Waldo Emerson
      - To Mrs. Burley, 1838 Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - To Child, Calvin G., 1859 Aug 25 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - To Cowdin, Elliot C. (Elliot Christopher), 1846 Sep 22 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - To Mrs. Drury, 1851 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - To Mr. Dudley, 1859 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - To Leighton, J. J., 1871 Feb 26 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - To Norton, Jane, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - To Pugh, T. B., 1869 Aug 3 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - To Robinson, W. S., undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - To Ross, Alexander Milton [fragment], undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - To Tucker, Elizabeth W., 1832 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 48)
        Copy in unidentified hand.
      - To Woodman, Horatio, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - To unidentified recipients, 1841-1860 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Letters to Ralph Waldo Emerson
      - Allingham, William, 1847-1851 (Box 1, Folder 51)
        Includes copy and poems
    - Third-party Correspondence
      - To Charles Ganz
        - British Journal of Photography, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 52)
        - Emerson, P. H. (Peter Henry), 1925-1933 (Box 1, Folder 53)
        - Royal Photographic Society of Great Britain, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 54)
        - Other correspondence, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Other Correspondence
      - Allingham, William to William Hepworth Dixon, 1861 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      - Emerson, Ellen Tucker to John Page Hopps, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 57)
      - Emerson, Ellen Tucker to Hannah Parsons, 1888 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Artwork
    - [Items transferred to YCAL MSS 902]
    - Engravings, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Lithograph by G. A. [Kincken?], 1881 (Box 61 (Broadside))
    - Photogravure by C. Taber Co., circa 1880
    - Photographs of Emerson, 1880, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
      Includes photographs by the Curtiss Studio and Warren; and photograph of Emerson's home in Concord, Massachusetts.
  - Other Material
    - Envelope addressed to James Edward Lewis in Emerson's hand, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Signatures, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Oversize
  - Engraving of Emerson, undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 65)
  - Photogravure of Emerson, circa 1880 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 66)